Guide to the Moses F. Little Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Moses F. Little papers
1841-1916
WA MSS S-1028
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.43
(58 volumes in 8 boxes)
A collection of 58 journals recording 72 years of Moses Little's life. He spent 1844-1848 aboard the whaler Arnolda, commanded by Captain D. U. Coffin out of New Bedford, Massachusetts. In 1849, Little joined the Sagamore Mining and Trading Company of Lynn, Massachusetts, and traveled to California, returning in 1851. Making a second trip to California in 1852 via the Isthmus to Panama City, he sailed on the Tennessee. He staked a claim in Sandy Gulch, Calaveras County, and returned to New York in 1853. Except for his trips to Chicago in 1869 visiting the stockyards and 1893 for the World's Fair, the remaining journals concern Little's life in Hill, New Hampshire, where he ran a general store and became interested in local politics.
Little, Moses F., 1823-1917?
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Goodspeed's Book Shop, Inc.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Available on microfilm.
Moses F. Little
Moses F. Little was born on August 31, 1823, in Boscawen, New Hampshire, and lived most of his life in the small town of Hill nearby. After graduating from an academy in Salisbury, New Hampshire, and receiving a certificate to teach in district schools, he spent the years 1844 to 1848 on a whaling voyage, and 1849 to 1853 mining for gold in California. Following his return to Hill, he became a shopkeeper, and served as town clerk and justice of the peace.
Scope and Contents
A collection of fifty-eight journals recording seventy-two years of Moses Little's life. He spent 1844-1848 aboard the whaler Arnolda, commanded by Captain D. U. Coffin out of New Bedford, Massachusetts. In 1849, Little joined the Sagamore Mining and Trading Company of Lynn, Massachusetts, and traveled to California over the plains and Rockies to Sacramento, returning in 1851. Making a second trip to California in 1852 via the Isthmus to Panama City, he sailed on the Tennessee. He staked a claim in Sandy Gulch, Calaveras County, and returned to New York via Nicaragua in 1853. Except for his trips to Chicago in 1869 visiting the stockyards and 1893 for the World's Fair, the remaining journals concern Little's life in Hill, New Hampshire, where he ran a general store, and became interested in local politics.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
General stores -- New Hampshire; Gold mines and mining -- California; Overland journeys to the Pacific; Voyages to the Pacific coast; Whaling; Azores; Bonin Islands (Japan); Calaveras County (Calif.); California -- Description and travel; Easter Island; Hawaii; Hebrides (Scotland); Hill (N.H.); New Bedford (Mass.); Oregon National Historic Trail; Pitcairn Islands; Sacramento (Calif.); Society Islands (French Polynesia); Sutter's Fort (Sacramento, Calif.); Account books -- United States; Diaries -- United States; Gold miners -- California; Merchants -- New Hampshire; Whalers (Persons) -- Massachusetts; Overland journeys to the Pacific -- 1849; Coffin, D. U.; Little, Eben L., b. 1837; Little, John Pierce, b. 1831; Little, Moses F., 1823-1917?; Amethyst (Ship: 1800); Arnolda (Ship); Brother Jonathan (Ship); Commodore Preble (Ship); Congaree (Ship); Desdemona (Ship); Elizabeth (Ship); Henry (Ship: 1848-1859); John Adams (Ship); Liancourt (Ship); Lydia (Ship); Mary Anne (Ship); Minerva (Ship: 1800-1807); Nantucket (Ship); Navigator (Ship); New Bedford (Ship); Nobile (Ship); Norman (Ship); Old Prometheus (Ship); Phoenix (Steamer); Rose (Ship); Sagamore Mining and Trading Company; Sophie (Steamer); Swift (Ship); World's Columbian Exposition ( 1893 Chicago, Ill.)
- Diaries and Other Manuscripts, 1841-1916; Series I; 3.43; (58 volumes in 8 boxes)
  - Copy book of proverbs, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Copy book of poems, 1841-1843 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Journal of the whaling voyage on ship Arnolda to the Pacific, 1844-1848 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Copies of 8 letters written during whaling voyage, 1844-1848 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Copy book of songs, 1845-1847 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Journal of overland travel from Lynn, Massachusetts over Oregon Trail and through South Pass, and mining in California, 1849-1850 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Extracts from the Mormon's Guide," copy, 1849 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Diary of mining in California, 1850 April-September (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Company account book in California, 1851 January-September (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Diary at home, 1851 December 31-1852 January 20 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Diary at home, description of California flora and fauna in the back, 1852 February-June (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Diary of second trip to California via isthmus of Panama and mining in California, 1852 June-December (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Book of expenses at Sandy Gulch gold mine, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Diary of mining in California and voyage home via Nicaragua, 1853 January-August (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Diary at home, 1853 August-1854 September (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Book of expenses, 1853 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Diary, 1854 September-1855 July (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Diary, 1855 July-October (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Diary, 1855 November 5-12 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Diary, 1855 November 17-December 18 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Diary, 1855 December 18-1856 January 17 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Diary, 1856 January 17-July 20 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Diary, 1856 July 21-1857 August 7 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Diary, 1857 August 29-December 23 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Diary, 1857 December 26-1858 February 22 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Diary, 1858 February 24-December 31 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Book of debts, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Diary, 1859 January-April (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Diary, 1859 September 21-December 31 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Diary, 1860 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Diary, 1864 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Diary, 1867 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Diary, 1869 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Diary, 1871 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Diary, 1877 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Diary, 1878 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Diary, 1880 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Diary, 1881 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Diary, 1882 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Diary, 1883 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Diary, 1884 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Diary, 1886 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Diary, 1887 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Diary, 1890 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Diary, 1891 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Diary, 1892 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Diary: trip to World's Fair in Chicago, 1893 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Diary, 1895 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Diary, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Diary, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Diary, 1904 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Diary, 1906 (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - Diary, 1907 (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - Diary, 1908 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - Diary, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - Diary, 1912 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Diary, 1915 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Diary, 1916 (Box 8, Folder 58)